# SZYMON KLARMAN

**Curriculum Vitae** 

# **Personal details**

Born:

1981. Poland

Homepage:

http://klarman.me

E-mail:

szymon@klarman.me

Networks:

LinkedIn, Google Scholar, Medium, Twitter, GitHub, SlideShare

# **Profile**

An R&D specialist in **knowledge engineering** with particular interest in connected data technologies:

- ✓ 10+ years of **R&D experience** in academia and industry
- ✓ Deep interest in knowledge technologies
- ✓ Strong analytical, communication and organizational skills
- ✓ Experience in individual and team-based project work
- ✓ Enthusiasm for **learning** and exploring new problems

**Expertise:** knowledge engineering, knowledge representation, automated reasoning, semantics, ontologies, taxonomies, linked data, graph data, open data publishing, algorithm design, data modelling, natural language processing, computational & probabilistic logics, basic data mining and machine learning, prototyping

# **Current role**

June **2018** - now Warsaw, Poland

# Owner / knowledge engineer

Epistemik

- consulting and delivering bespoke knowledge engineering solutions (data models and architectures, ontologies, algorithms, natural language processing pipelines, software prototypes, microservice architectures, etc.)
- advocating linked/graph data and semantic techniques for knowledge applications
- driving R&D activities within projects employing AI technologies
- current and past clients, predominantly within start-up and non-profit space, include:
  - Stockholm Environment Institute (Sweden) solution architect & developer
  - UN Division for Sustainable Development Goals (US) linked data consultant
  - Granthika (US/Canada) director of R&D
  - Neural Alpha (UK) knowledge architect
  - Data to Value (UK) ontology consultant

# **Previous experience**

2017 - 2018

London, United Kingdom

#### Knowledge architect

**Semantic Integration** 

- developing a microservices-based data architecture as an onsite consultant at PhotoBox
- initiated and lead the development of the open-source project HyperGraphQL: a GraphQL interface for querying linked data
- consulting and delivering R&D contributions towards diverse PoCs and prototypes

2016 - 2017 London, United Kingdom

## R&D engineer

Grakn Labs

- R&D work by the design and development of GRAKN knowledge graph platform; involved primarily in designing the underlying knowledge representation model
- gathering requirements, knowledge engineering and writing data transformation scripts in the context of PoC applications
- benchmarking query and reasoning performance of selected graph databases

2015 - 2016 London, United Kingdom

#### Research fellow

Brunel University London / Department of Computer Science

- research work by the DARPA's Big Mechanism programme (goal: development of novel AI
  technology for extracting, assembling and explaining large mechanistic models described in
  the cancer biology literature to facilitate future scientific discovery)
- responsible for developing the knowledge assembly system (based on the application of semantic and probabilistic/statistical inference tools/techniques), and maintaining the knowledge graph for the project consortium

2013 - 2015 Pretoria, South Africa

#### Postdoctoral researcher

CSIR Meraka Institute & University of KwaZulu-Natal / Centre for Artificial Intelligence Research

- independent research work (main themes: *ontology-based access to temporal data, abductive reasonind*)
- research work by MomConnect project (goal: implementation of a mobile platform for supporting pregnant women in rural Africa)

2008 - 2012 Amsterdam. Netherlands

#### Ph.D. research assistant

VU University Amsterdam / Knowledge Representation & Reasoning Group

 research work towards the doctoral degree (main theme: formal mechanisms for managing contexts in Description Logic ontologies)

**2007 - 2008** Amsterdam, Netherlands

#### Research assistant

University of Amsterdam / Leibniz Center for Law

 research and knowledge engineering work by the ESTRELLA project (goal: development of the Legal Knowledge Interchange Format)

**2005 - 2006** Dublin, Ireland

## Data entry operator

Millward Brown

processing and curating data from marketing research surveys

# **Education**

2008 - 2013

Amsterdam, Netherlands

2006 - 2008

Amsterdam, Netherlands

2000 - 2005

Lodz, Poland

## Ph.D. Artificial Intelligence

VU University Amsterdam / Department of Computer Science

### M.Sc. Logic

University of Amsterdam / Institute for Logic, Language & Computation

## M.A. Philosophy

University of Lodz / Institute of Philosophy

# **Other**

#### Awards & honors:

- best student paper award (with V. Gutierrez-Basulto) at the International Workshop on Description Logics (2011).
- Huygens Scholarship awarded by the Netherlands Organization for International Cooperation in Higher Education (2006-2007).
- cum laude distinction for the overall results in both master's programs (2005, 2008).
- distinction in the Competition for Master's Theses on Logic and Its Applications awarded by the Polish Association for Logic and Philosophy of Science (2005)

## **Community involvement:**

- **co-author** of 20+ publications in academic journals, conference and workshop proceedings
- **co-organizer** or **program committee** member for 10+ international conferences and workshops
- quest editor of a special issue of the International Journal of Approximate Reasoning
- reviewer for 20+ international journals, conferences and workshops
- visiting researcher at University of Edinburgh, FBK Trento, University of Bremen, TU Dresden
- **invited speaker** at Connected Data London Conference 2016-17, Semantic Web London Meetup 2017, Connected Data London Meetup 2016

#### Teaching:

- introduction to description logics for M.Sc. Artificial Intelligence (VU University Amsterdam, 2009-2012); philosophy & ethics classes for school children (2004)
- co-supervising master's projects for M.Sc. Artificial Intelligence (VU University Amsterdam).

## Languages:

English (full professional proficiency); German, Dutch (basic, passive); Polish (mother tongue)